Guide to the Ann Imlah Schneider Papers, 1959-2014 and undated RL.11715
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ann Imlah Schneider papers
1959-2014 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Schneider, Ann Imlah
RL.11715
10.7 Linear Feet
Ann Imlah Schneider's most extensive and recent government service was at the U.S. Department of Education, where she was senior program officer for several of the Education Department's grant programs for international education, under Title VI (of the Higher Education Act). Collection primarily includes publications regarding issues in education, including foreign languages and international and area studies, study abroad, internationalization, business education, and teaching. There are also research files on international education and foreign languages, area studies, Title VI, and governmental regulations; files regarding Schneider's work with Title VI higher education centers for international and area studies; and files related to the Center for Education within the U.S. Department of Education, primarily regarding appropriations.
Biographical / Historical
Ann Imlah Schneider's most extensive and recent government service was at the U.S. Department of Education, where she was senior program officer for several of the Education Department's grant programs for international education, under Title VI (of the Higher Education Act). Her experience also includes work on government-academic relations at the State Department, as well as earlier positions with the senior Fulbright program and with the American Friends Service Committee.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Ann Imlah Schneider Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2018.
Collection Overview
Collection primarily includes publications regarding issues in education, including foreign languages and international and area studies, study abroad, internationalization, business education, and teaching. There are also research files on international education and foreign languages, area studies, Title VI, and governmental regulations; files regarding Schneider's work with Title VI higher education centers for international and area studies; and files related to the Center for Education within the U.S. Department of Education, primarily regarding appropriations.
Area studies -- Study and teaching -- United States; Federal aid to higher education -- United States; Foreign study -- United States; Globalization -- Study and teaching -- United States; International education -- United States; Language and languages -- Study and teaching -- United States; Schneider, Ann Imlah; United States. Department of Education; United States. Department of Education -- Officials and employees
- Publications, 1959-2014 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes articles, serials, books, and reports regarding issues in education, with emphasis on higher education, and particularly, foreign languages and international and area studies. Other topics include study abroad, internationalization, business education, and teaching.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - 1970 Census of International Education in State Colleges and Universities, 1970 November (Box 1, Folder 21)
    by Edward J. F. Glavin
  - The Academic Profession: An International Perspective, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    by Ernest L. Boyer, Philip G. Altbach, and Mary Jean Whitelaw
  - ADFL (Association of Departments of Foreign languages) Bulletin, 1990, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    v. 22, no. 1; v. 32, no. 1 (2 copies)
  - American Students and Teachers Abroad: Sources of Information about Overseas Study, Teaching, Work, and Travel, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Revised Edition
    by Pat Kern McIntyre
  - Apples and Oranges in the Flat World: A Layperson's Guide to International Comparisons of Postsecondary Education, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    by Jane V. Wellman
  - Area Studies on U.S. Campuses: A Directory, 1971 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Asia in the Schools: Preparing Young Americans for Today's Interconnected World, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AUCC [Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada] Internationalization Survey Update, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    by Jane Knight
  - Benchmarking for Success: Ensuring U.S. Students Receive a World-Class Education, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Beyond Growth: The Next Stage in Language and Area Studies, 1984 April (Box 5)
  - Bibliographical Resources about India: An Annotated List of English-Language Reference Works Published in India, 1965-70, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    compiled by Kiki Skagen
  - Building a Strategic Framework for Comprehensive Internationalization, 2005 November (Box 1, Folder 3)
    by Christa I. Olson, Madeleine F. Green, and Barbara A Hill
  - Bulletin of International Interchanges, 1988 February (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Vol. 27
    "Fulbright's Fortieth: Culture and Power Revisited"
    by Richart T. Arndt, David Bame, and Steven A. Blodgett
  - Campus Trends 1995: New Directions for Academic Programs, 1995 July (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Higher Education Panel Report, Number 85
    By Elaine El-Khawas
  - Change: The Magazine of Higher Learning, 2002-2013; 3 items (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Changing Perspectives on International Education, 2001 (Box 5)
    edited by Patrick O'Meara, Howard D. Mehlinger, and Roxana Ma Newman
  - Citizens for the 21st Century: Revitalizing the Civic Mission of Schools, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Collaboration Between K-12 and Higher Education Institutions, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - College: The Undergraduate Experience in America, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    by Ernest L. Boyer
  - College-Bound Students' Interests in Study Abroad and Other International Learning Activities, 2008 January (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Current Issues in Higher Education, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Faculty Career Development
  - Current Issues in Higher Education, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    No. 2
    Creating An Integrated Curriculum
    by Harlan Cleveland, Mary Jim Josephs, John Nichols, and Susan Gurewitsch
  - Current Issues in Higher Education, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    No. 3
    Partnerships with Business and the Professions by K. Patricia Cross, Ernest A. Lynton, Philip N. Nowlen, and Milton R. Stern
  - Data from the Annual Survey: State Student Assessment Programs, 1999 Fall (Box 4)
    vols. I and II
  - The Degree Qualifications Profile, 2011 January (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Directory of Federal Historical Programs and Activities, 1998 June (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Diversity Digest, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Vol. 8 No. 3
  - Educating Americans for a World in Flux: Ten Ground Rules for Internationalizing Higher Education, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Educating Researchers, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    by Arthur Levine
  - Education for Global Interdependence: A Report with Recommendations to the Government/Academic Interface Committee, 1975 October (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Education for International Competence in Pennsylvania, 1988 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
    edited by Andrew Dinniman, Burkart Holzner
  - Education Update, 2009 January (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Vol. 51 No. 1
  - Educational Leadership, 2004 December/2005 January (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Vol. 62 No. 4
  - Enhancing Education in International Affairs, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1993 Case Catalog
  - Expanding Education Abroad at U.S. Community Colleges, 2008 September (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Metting America's Global Education Challenge Issue 3
  - Expanding the International Dimension of Higher Education, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Expanding the International Scope of Universities, 2000 May (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Expanding the Vision of Foreign Language Education: Enter the Less Commonly Taught Languages, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    by A. Ronald Walton
  - Federal Funding for International Studies: Does It Help? Does It Matter?, [1999] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Ann Imlah Schneider and Barbara B. Burn
  - Federal Support for International Studies: The Role of NDEA Title VI, 1981 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
    by Lorraine M. McDonnell, Sue E. Berryman, and Douglas Scott
  - Federal Support for Training Foreign Language and Area Specialists: The Education and Careers of FLAS Fellowship Recipients, 1983 September (Box 1, Folder 12)
    by Lorraine M. McDonnell, with Cathleen Stasz and Rodger Madison
  - A Field Guide to Internationalizing Business Education, 2000 (Box 5)
    Edited by Robert F. Sherer, Sarah T. Beaton, M. Fall Ainina, and Jeffrey F. Meyer
  - Foreign Language and International Studies Specialists: The Marketplace and National Policy, 1979 September; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    by Sue E. Berryman, Paul F. Langer, John Pincus, and Richard H. Solomon, with the assistance of Ellen H. Gelbard and Priscilla M. Schlegel
  - Foreign Language Instruction in the United States: A National Survey of Elementary and Secondary Schools, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    by Nancy C. Rhodes and Lucinda E. Branaman
  - Foreign Language Planning in the United States, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    by Richard D. Lambert
  - The Foreign Undergraduate Student: Institutional Priorities for Action, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Four Decades of Middle Eastern Study, 1987 Winter (Box 1, Folder 15)
    by R. Bayly Winder
  - Fulbright at Fifty, 1997 July (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Geography in Internationalizing the Undergraduate Curriculum, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    edited by Salvatore J. Natoli and Andrew R. Bond
  - Global Education Checklist for Teachers, Schools, School Systems and Sate Education Agencies, 2002-2003; 2 copies (Box 6, Folder 4)
    No. 173 by Fred Czarra
  - Global Perspective, 1995 Spring (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Vol. 7, No. 2
    "Internationalizing the Undergraduate Experience"
  - Global Preparedness and Human Resources: College and Corporate Perspectives, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    by T. K. Bikson and S. A. Law
  - Globalization and the Challenges of a New Century: A Reader, 2000 (Box 5)
    edited by Patrick O'Meara, Howard D. Mehlinger, and Matthew Krain
  - Guidelines for International Teacher Education, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - IIE Networker, 2006 Fall (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Improving University Teaching: Proceedings, 1980 July 9-11 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - In the International Interest: The Contributions and Needs of America's International Liberal Arts Colleges, 1992 January (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Increasing Foreign Language Capacity Conference, Montreal....: Proceedings, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Edited by Nancy J. Church and Jennifer R. Karchmer
  - Increasing US Global Competitiveness through International Business Education: 20 Years of CIBER, 1989-2009, 2010? (Box 6, Folder 5)
    by Susanna Easton, Jana Blakestad, and Kelly Murphrey
  - Inspire: Infusing and Nurturing the Skills and Practice of Inquiry and Research in Education, 2005 January (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Instruction in Diplomacy: The Liberal Arts Approach, 1972 April (Box 1, Folder 19)
    edited by Smith Simpson
  - Intercultural Education in the Two-Year College: A Handbook on Strategies for Change, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    edited by Jorge M. Pérez Ponce
  - International and Area Studies Resources: A Selected Guide, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    compiled and edited by Robert Goehlert, Roberta Astroff, Anthony Stamatoplos
  - International and Language Education for a Global Future: Fifty Years of U.S. Title VI and Fulbright-Hays Programs, 2010 (Box 5)
    edited by David S. Wiley and Robert S. Glew
  - International Competence: A Key to America's Future: A Plan of Action prepared by the Coalition for the Advancement of Foreign Languages and International Studies (CAFLIS), 1989 December (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The International Dimension of American Teacher Education: A Survey of International Education in Teacher Education Programs of American Colleges and Universities, 1972 (Box 4)
    by Frank H. Klassen, David G. Imig and Joost Yff
  - International Education and Foreign Languages: Keys to Securing America's Future, 2007 (Box 5)
    edited by Mary Ellen O'Connell and Janet L. Norwood
  - International Education Administrators In U.S. Higher Education: A Directory, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - International Education Forum, 1996 Spring (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Vol. 16, no. 1
  - International Education in the New Global Era: Proceedings of a National Policy Conference on the Higher Education Act, Title VI, and Fulbright-Hays Programs, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    edited by John N. Hawkins, Carlos Manuel Haro, Miriam A. Kazanjian, Gilbert W. Merkx, and David Wiley
  - International Education Programs of the U.S. Government: An Inventory, 1980 (Box 4)
    compiled by Helen R. Wiprud
  - International Educator, 2006-2014; 2 folders 9 issues (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
  - International Human Rights and International Education, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    by Thomas Buergenthal and Judith V. Torney
  - International Opportunities for U.S. Educators, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Programs and Centers for Instruction, Research and Public Service in the Western States (including instruction in less common foreign languages), 1986 April (Box 2, Folder 2)
    edited by Frank C. Abbott
  - International Role of the University in the Eighties, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - International Studies and the Social Sciences: A Survey of the Status of International/Comparative Studies and Recommendations Concerning National Needs and Priorities, 1971 June (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - International Studies and the Social Sciences: Problems, Priorities and Prospects in the United States, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Vol. 2 Sage Library of Social Research
    by James N. Rosenau
  - International Studies and the Undergraduate, 1989; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - International Studies Association: Panel Presentations from the ISA National Convention, Washington, D.C., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - International Studies Association Proceedings: Crises and Concepts in International Affairs, 1965 April (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Sixth Annual Meeting
    by Kenneth E. Boulding, Edmund A. Gullion, Robert A. Scalapino, Metin Tamkoc, and W. Howard Wriggins
  - International Studies for Undergraduates, 1987 Operations and Opinions, 1988 September (Box 2, Folder 9)
    by Charles J. Andersen
  - International Studies Notes of the International Studies Association, 1977-1999; 8 items (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - International Studies: Present Status and Future Prospects, 1971 October (Box 2, Folder 12)
    edited by Fred W. Riggs
  - International Studies Quarterly, 1967-1982; 6 items (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - International Studies Review: A Staff Study, 1979 September (Box 2, Folder 16)
    by Elinor G. Barber and Warren Ilchman
  - Internationalization of U.S. Higher Education: Preliminary Status Report 2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    by Fred M. Hayward
  - Internationalization: Rhetoric or Reality?, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    ACLS Occasional paper No. 56 by Sheila Biddle
  - Internationalizing American Higher Education: Innovation and Structural Change, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    by Ellen McDonald Gumperz
  - Internationalizing Business Education: Meeting the Challenge, 1993 (Box 5)
    edited by S. Tamer Cavusgill
  - Internationalizing the Campus: A User's Guide, 2003 August (Box 2, Folder 18)
    by Madeleine F. Green and Christa Olson
  - Internationalizing Teacher Education: What Can Be Done?, 2003 April (Box 2, Folder 18)
    by Ann Imlah Schneider
  - Internationalizing the Undergraduate Curriculum: A Handbook for Campus Leaders, 1992; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 19)
    by Sarah Pickert and Barbara Turlington
  - Investing in Human Capital: Leadership for the Challenges of the 21st Century, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Issues in Global Education, 1996, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Nos. 135 and 136, 151
  - Japanese Language Instruction in the United States: Resources, Practice, and Investment Strategy, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    by Eleanor H. Jordan with Richard D. Lambert
  - Journal of Studies in International Education, 2001 Winter (Box 2, Folder 21)
    vol. 5, no. 4
  - Key State Education Policies on K-12 Education: 2000 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Language and Area Centers: 1959-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Language and Area Centers: A Report on the First 5 Years, 1964; 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    by Donald N. Bigelow and Lyman H. Legters
  - Language and Area Studies Review, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Language and Area Study Programs in American Universities, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    compiled by Larry Moses
  - Language and International Studies: A Richard Lambert Perspective, 1993 (Box 4)
    edited by Sarah Jane Moore and Christine A. Morfit
  - Language and National Security for the 21st Century: The Federal Role in Supporting National Language Capacity, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    by Richard D. Brecht and William P. Rivers
  - Language and National Security in the 21st Century: The Role of Title Vi/Fulbright-Hays in Supporting National Language Capacity, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    By Richard D. Brecht and William P. Rivers
  - The Language Educator, 2006-2007 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Vol. 1 Issue 5, Vol. 2 Issue 6
  - Language Planning Around the World: Contexts and Systemic Change, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    edited by Richard D. Lambert
  - Language Study and International Business: A Handbook for Students, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Learning from Success: Campus Case Studies in International Program Development, 1996 (Box 4)
    by Ann Kellcher
  - The Liberal Arts and Teacher Education: A Confrontation, 1971 December (Box 4)
    edited by Donald N. Bigelow
  - Mapping Internationalization on U.S. Campuses, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    by Laura Siaya and Fred M. Hayward
  - Measuring Internationalization at Community Colleges, 2005 June (Box 3, Folder 3)
    by Madeleine F. Green and Laura Siaya
  - Meeting the Highly Qualified Teachers Challenge: The Secretary's Annual Report on Teacher Quality, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Model Standards for Licensing Beginning Foreign Language Teachers: A Resource for State Dialogue, 2002 June (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Draft for comments
  - A National Action Agenda for Internationalizing Higher Education, 2007 October (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - National Profile of Community Colleges: Trends & Statistics, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    4th ed. by Kent A. Phillippe and Leila González Sullivan
  - The New College Course Map and Transcript Files: Changes in Course-Taking and Achievement, 1972-1993, 1995 October (Box 3, Folder 4)
    by Clifford Adelman
  - New Directions in International Education, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    The Preservation of the Cosmopolitan Research University in the United States: The Prospect for the 1980s
  - New Directions in Language and Area Studies: Priorities for the 1980's, 1979 May (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Edited by Donald R. Shea and Maureen J. Smith
  - North Carolina in the World: Preparing North Carolina Teachers for an Interconnected World, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - On Change: En Route to Transformation, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    by Peter Eckel, Barbara Hill, and Madeleine Green
  - An Overview of Higher Education in the United States: Diversity, Access, and the Role of the Marketplace, 2004 October (Box 3, Folder 5)
    by Peter D. Eckel and Jacqueline E. King
  - Pew Case Studies in International Affairs & Institute for the Study of Diplomacy Books, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Phi Delta Kappan, 2004 November (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Points of Leverage: An Agenda for a National Foundation for International Studies, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Power of Tests: The Impact of Language Tests on Teaching and Learning, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    by Elana Shohamy
  - Predictors of Foreign Language Gain during Study Abroad, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    by Richard D. Brecht, Dan Davidson, and Ralph B. Ginsberg
  - Preparing Global Professionals for the New Century: Issues, Curricula and Strategies for International Affairs Education, 1998 November (Box 3, Folder 7)
    edited by Michele Cisco Titi
  - President's Commission on Foreign Language and International Studies: Background Papers and Studies, 1979 November; 2 copies (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - Principal Indicators of Student Academic Histories in Postsecondary Education, 1972-2000, 2004 March (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Professional Schools of International Affairs on the Eve of the 21st Century, 1994 December (Box 3, Folder 10)
    by Louis W. Goodman, Kay King, and Stephen F. Szabo
  - Project 30 Year Two Report: Institutional Accomplishments, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Prospects for Faculty in Area Studies, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Public Experience, Attitudes, and Knowledge: A Report on Two National Surveys about International Education, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    by Fred M. Hayward and Laura M. Siaya
  - Reform in International Studies: Memorandum to the President's Commission, 1978 November (Box 3, Folder 12)
    by Roger Paget
  - The Reform of Teacher Education for the 21st Century: Project 30 Year One Report, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    by Frank B. Murray and Daniel Fallon
  - Reforming the Higher Education Curriculum: Internationalizing the Campus, 1998 (Box 4)
    edited by Josef A. Mestenhauser and Brenda J. Ellingboe
  - Report to the Congress of the United States: Study of Foreign Languages and Related Areas, 1978 September 13 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Role of Federal Programs in Internationalizing the U.S. Higher Education System from 1958-1988, 1994 (Box 5)
    Ph.D. dissertation
    by Nancy L. Ruther
  - The Senior International Officer (SIO) as Change Agent, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    by John D. Heyl
  - Social Education, 1998, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Vol. 62 No. 5, Vol. 71 No. 1
  - Social Studies and the Young Learner, 2008 March/April (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Vol. 20 No. 4
  - The Spaces between Numbers: Getting International Data on Higher Education Straight, 2009 November (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Spotlight on FIPSE [Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education] International Programs, 2005 November (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Spreading the Word: Improving the Way We Teach Foreign Languages, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Spreading the Word II: Promising Developments for Undergraduate Foreign Language Instruction, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Strategy for a Global University, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    edited by Gill-Chin Lim
  - Stepping Forward As Stewards of Place: A Guide for Leading Public Engagement at State Colleges and Universities, 2002 May (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Strength Through Wisdom: A Critique of U.S. Capability, 1979 November (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Strengthening Study Abroad: Recommendations for Effective Institutional Management for Presidents, Senior Administrators, and Study Abroad Professionals, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Student Development in College: Theory, Research and Practice, 1998 (Box 4)
    by Nancy J. Evas, Deanna S. Forney, and Florence Guido-DiBrito
  - The Study of Europe in the United States, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    by Christopher J. Makins
  - Taking Business into the 21st Century: Ten-Year Accomplishments of the Title VI Centers for International Business Education (CIBERs), 1989-1999 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Teacher Preparation for the Global Age: The Imperative for Change, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Three Decades of Excellence, 1965-1994: The Fulbright-Hays Doctoral Dissertation Research Abroad Fellowship Program and Its Impact on the American Academy, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - To Leave No Teacher Behind: Building International Competence into the Undergraduate Training of K-12 Teachers, 2007 May (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - To Strengthen the Nation's Investment in Foreign Languages and International Studies: A Legislative Proposal, 1986 October 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Draft